Guide to the John Simon Papers TAM.853
Tamiment Library and Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives
John Simon Papers
1955-2015
Tamiment Library and Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives
Simon, John (John J.)
Katherine Dobkin Living Trust
TAM.853
2.09 Linear Feet in 5 manuscript boxes and 2 folders in shared housing
765.9 Megabytes in 1 recording
John J. Simon (1934-2022) was an editor, writer, and broadcaster whose life and work intersected with many aspects of Left politics and culture. Simon was a producer for WNET (Channel 13) and a general manager of WBAI. Simon's career in publishing started in mainstream circles at Random House and Knopf, but while at Knopf he met his mentor, the radical editor Angus Cameron, and under his guidance, became known as an editor capable of getting Left-leaning works published by conventional publishing houses. Simon was critical in publishing works by the Black Panthers including Stokely Carmichael and Charles V. Hamilton's Black Power: the Politics of Liberation in America. The John Simon Papers (dated 1955-2015) consist of materials created and collected by Simon documenting his career as an editor, writer, and broadcaster of the radical Left. Materials include correspondence, memoranda, notes, ephemera, clippings, and publications. Multiple files include Simon's proposals for editorial and publishing ventures.
Scope and Contents
The John Simon Papers (dated 1955-2015) consist of materials created and collected by Simon documenting his career as an editor, writer, and broadcaster of the radical Left. Materials include correspondence, memoranda, notes, ephemera, clippings, and publications. Multiple files include Simon's proposals for editorial and publishing ventures.
Conditions Governing Access
Materials are open without restrictions.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Donated by the Katherine Dobkin Living Trust in May 2025; the accession number associated with this gift is 2025.057.
Arrangement
This collection has not been arranged by an archivist. The materials are arranged in the order in which they were received from the donor.
Biographical Note
John J. Simon (1934-2022) was an editor, writer, and broadcaster whose life and work intersected with many aspects of Left politics and culture. Simon was a producer for WNET (Channel 13) and a general manager of WBAI. Simon's career in publishing started in mainstream circles at Random House and Knopf, but while at Knopf he met his mentor, the radical editor Angus Cameron, and under his guidance, became known as an editor capable of getting Left-leaning works published by conventional publishing houses. Simon was critical in publishing works by the Black Panthers including Stokely Carmichael and Charles V. Hamilton's Black Power: the Politics of Liberation in America. He was director of the Monthly Review Foundation and on the editorial boards of Monthly Review and Monthly Review Press.
Appraisal
One photograph of an unidentified child was appraised out of the collection.
Periodical editors; Radio broadcasters; Publishers and publishing; Katherine Dobkin Living Trust; WBAI Radio (New York, N.Y.); WNET (Television station: New York, N.Y.)
- FBI File, 1981 (Box 1, Folder 1)
- Funders Lists -- Modern Times, 1984 (Box 1, Folder 2-3)
- Argonaut Rev Lists, undated (Box 1, Folder 4)
- Argonaut Lists, 1992 (Box 1, Folder 5)
- Undergraduate Senior Project -- "The Foundations of Natural Law and the Growth of the American Republic", 1956 (Box 1, Folder 6)
- Belfrage, Sally, 1985-1994 (Box 1, Folder 7)
- Ramp Publishing Company, 1971-1996 (Box 1, Folder 8-9)
- Argonaut Press, 1974-1996 (Box 1, Folder 10)
- Rabinowitz Foundation, 1988 (Box 1, Folder 11-12, Box 2, Folder 1)
- NPR Publications Project, undated (Box 2, Folder 2)
- New Magazine Project, 1963-1967 (Box 2, Folder 3-4)
- Black College Students, 1982 (Box 2, Folder 5)
- Publishing Experience, undated (Box 2, Folder 6)
- Ramp Publishing Company -- Incorporation, 1971-1974 (Box 2, Folder 7)
- Studies on the Left, 1961-1962 (Box 2, Folder 8)
- WBAI -- 1977 Crisis, 1976-1986 (Box 2, Folder 9-10)
- WBAI -- General, 1982-1987 (Box 2, Folder 11-12)
- Writing and Publishing, 1962-1981 (Box 2, Folder 13-14)
- Mao Zedong Biography, 1970 (Box 3, Folder 1)
- Correspondence, 1979-1981 (Box 3, Folder 2-3)
- Pacifica Radio, 1984-1986 (Box 3, Folder 4)
- WBAI -- Direct Mail, 1986 (Box 3, Folder 5)
- WBAI -- Grant Proposals, 1986 (Box 3, Folder 6)
- Original Writings, undated (Box 3, Folder 7)
- Writers' Fund Agency Proposal, undated (Box 3, Folder 8)
- Publishing, 1985 (Box 3, Folder 9)
- Book Lists, 1960-1961 (Box 3, Folder 10)
- Pacifica Radio Manuals, 1986, undated (Box 3, Folder 11)
- Magazine Proposal, undated (Box 3, Folder 12)
- World Policy Institute, 1985 (Box 3, Folder 13)
- Resumes, 1984 (Box 3, Folder 14)
- FBI File, 1990 (Box 3, Folder 15)
- Interview Follow-ups, 1985 (Box 3, Folder 16)
- Proposals, undated (Box 3, Folder 17)
- WBAI -- Board Meetings, 1985 (Box 3, Folder 18)
- WBAI -- History, 1984-1987 (Box 3, Folder 19-20)
- Bard Papers, 1956 (Box 3, Folder 21)
- Bard Psychology Journal, 1956 (Box 3, Folder 22)
- Yale Law Journal, 1981 (Box 4, Folder 1)
- Monthly Review, 1998, 2001 (Box 4, Folder 2)
- Monthly Review, 2003 (Box 4, Folder 3)
- Monthly Review, 2005 (Box 4, Folder 4)
- Monthly Review, 2009, 2015 (Box 4, Folder 5)
- Monthly Review -- 50th Anniversary Celebration, 1999; TW_TAM_853_ER_1
- Israels, Elizabeth, 1957 (Box 4, Folder 6-7)
- Publishing, 1981 (Box 4, Folder 8-9)
- Correspondence, Clippings, Notes, 1992-1995 (Box 4, Folder 10)
- Correspondence, 1982-1984 (Box 4, Folder 11)
- Editorial, 1982 (Box 4, Folder 12)
- "Working Paper" Article, undated (Box 5, Folder 1)
- Magazine Project Proposal, 1974-1979 (Box 5, Folder 2)
- Resumes, Biographies, Professional Statements, undated (Box 5, Folder 3)
- Correspondence, Ephemera, Notes, 1974-1984 (Box 5, Folder 4)
- Writing and Publishing, circa 1977 (Box 5, Folder 5)
- Magazine Proposal, 1975, undated (Box 5, Folder 6)
- Baron, Phyllis, 1958 (Box 5, Folder 7)
- Notes, Correspondence, 1980 (Box 5, Folder 8)
- Correspondence, 1974-1980 (Box 5, Folder 9)
- Mendelsohn, Ora, 1955 (Box 5, Folder 10)
- CALIF -- Fundraising and Edit, 1961-1982 (Box 5, Folder 11)
- Correspondence, 1971-1982 (Box 5, Folder 12-13, Box Shared Tamiment 200, Folder 19)
- Stuyvesant High School, undated (Box Shared Tamiment 200, Folder 20)